[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host joavan aspon and
today I will be discussing cell-based
architecture with asanka Abes Singa
asanka is the c wso2 Global
infrastructure software company and he
has over 20 years of experience in
designing and implementing highly
scalable distributed systems service
oriented and microservice architectures
he is a committer at the Apache software
foundation and the regular speaker at
numerous Global events and Tech meetups
aanka is the Creator and original author
of sale based architecture digital
double and the platform lless Manifesto
aanka welcome to software engineering
radio is there anything I miss that
you'd like to add no I didn't thinkk
thank you very much and it's a pleasure
to be here I watched your previous
episodes a very interesting podcast it's
honor to be here I think you gave a
really good introduction in addition to
that I have been in the industry for
nearly two decades Now work on these
large distributed systems and helping
many organizations to be successful in
their digital journey by implementing
application architecture and application
development in their different type of
business objectives so let's start with
giving our audience some context what is
a cell-based architecture yeah so
cell-based architecture is a
architecture style and it's a
combination of application deployment
and team architecture as well because
sometimes people just take it as a
deployment architecture that's why I
specifically mention that it's a
combination of of these three things and
during the podcast I will explain in
detail about how it aligns with these
three elements of application deployment
and team architecture so uh in a very
high level that's what it is and
addressing most of the uh challenges The
Architects developers and devops and
platform Engineers facing today I can
give a little bit history about how we
started as well and a little bit on why
we started and then we can get into the
concepts of the architecture style
because having some understanding about
how this idea came into the picture and
then why we implemented might be really
helpful for you to understand concept
then maybe we can start with what
problems aims at
solving yes it's basically this concept
or the idea came to our thinking around
2018 when microservices came into the
picture and people were blindly getting
into microservices and implementing
systems using microservice architecture
and if you can remember those days there
was a very famous diagram Called Death
Star diagram that represent thousand of
microservices connecting to each other
you can't understand how these things
are connected what are the dependencies
so and so forth so that's what we saw in
the diagram but it was more difficult
inside those organizations who
implemented these systems that they
didn't know who own these microservices
who's going to maintain it what's the
life cycle of a microservice so it
became a problem in the industry so
that's how the idea came into the
picture and then we were trying to find
a solution for that particular problem
so that was the primary issue and then
there's another thing that we identified
that's a gap between
architecture development and deployment
if I explain it in detail architect
architect something he or she will draw
some diagrams and then identify this
should be the architecture that the
system that they are building then
developer look at it and then they build
something by referring the architecture
more align with that but not exactly
what the architect architected in the
drawing boards or diagrams and then it
get worse when the developer develop
that thing and then give it to the
deployment or devops and operational
people they deploy something completely
different yes they have to have some
standards and then they need to look at
the security they need to look at what
are the best practices they follow so
basically there wasn't a connection in
between the architecture development and
deployment so we were looking at how we
can address that by creating an
architecture construct that you can take
from architecture to development to
deployment so that was the second
problem and then the there was another
thing that we identified this gap
between brown field and Green Field
people draw nice diagrams people try to
implement systems but reality inside the
Enterprise you can't ignore Brownfield
we build these systems for a decade or
two decades and you have lot of
databases you have Legacy systems
perfectly running inside the Enterprise
and consumed by many users so you need
to still use those data and systems and
build stuff on top of that there should
be a Synergy between brown field and
green field so we were looking for a
solution how you can bridge this Gap in
between brown field and green field and
then again at the same time we
identified people releasing reference
architectures but those reference
architectures are more kind of referent
implementations that bound to a specific
vendor technology and we wanted to
implement something or introduce
something that is completely technology
and the vendor neutral that the person
who's implementing can take it and use
it based on their technical architecture
and the preferred vendor products and
build it so those were the motivations
that we had and the problems that we are
addressing again the solution for those
problems that I framed in this
particular segment so a question so the
first one you mention the microservices
the proliferation of microservices in
companies so what do you want to address
there would you want to address because
you mentioned the ownership and
maintenance and do something with those
services but where are you trying to
address mainly the ownership problem or
other issues related to microservices
maybe related to I don't know reli ility
operability other aspects so both
actually because there was a
misunderstanding about the micro micro
people took it as the size but
microservices doesn't mean it's size
it's the scope so how you can design
microservices properly and then have a
single scope to a one service is where
the true microservice architecture is
coming but when it comes to Enterprise
micro service is too granular it's too
small for a team to work and team to
operate so that's where you need to have
a way that you can group set of
microservices and then expose set of
capabilities from that group of
microservices so when you group it then
it becomes something a team can maintain
and I would look at it from a different
angle I'm sure that the listeners are
well aware of about domain driven design
something that heavily used inside the
Enterprises that you divide a bigger
problem into small chunks using domain
driven design so there was a angle to
that as well if you use domain driven
designs you can identify what are the
related microservices for a specific
domain so in in cell architecture we
will get into detail you can nicely
Implement domain M driven design by
grouping these micros that is a first
issue so once you do that then you can
have a proper dependency management as
well as you can have proper ownership
for that set of microservices and then
these things that you explain about
resiliency and then High availability
scalability those are coming in the
outer architecture of microservices not
the inner architecture of microservices
so sell architecture addressing both
can I ask you what do you mean with
outer architecture and inner
architecture yeah so the inner
architecture is basically the
capabilities that you put inside the
microservice and how you implement the
business logic inside those
microservices that's the inner
architecture mainly application
architecture related stuff outer
architecture is basically what you are
getting from the fabric because you are
not putting resiliency you are not
putting High availability inside the
microservice right it basically should
come from the place that you deploy this
stuff in in very high level uh it can be
the platform that you deploy or it can
be the infrastructure that you deploy
then only you can have a more scalable
system so that's the outer architecture
of microservices that you use those
capabilities from the platform as a
platform service and then get your
microservices scalable and higher
available there a gray area there as
well like whether the microservice is
stateful stateless because stateful and
stateless those type of things depending
on how you scale and how reliable these
stuff are so you need to a little bit
consider that when you are building the
in architecture or the application logic
but differentiating these two will help
you to have a more robust architecture
in the application Level okay and a
question that I want to ask because when
you look around for definition of
cell-based architecture there are
various places of course there is the
gab Brio where you put the reference
architecture there but there are also
other places and a recurring thing in
other places is that they mention that
the cell-based architecture is pretty
much something coming from the bulkhead
pattern so aimed at
resiliency yeah so if you go back to the
history a little bit the architecture
style introduced by myself and Paul
freemantle who was the founding CTO at
wso2 so we introduced this in 2018 after
that what we have seen there are a few
other parallels that referring cell
architecture and used it in different
context so in one of those references
it's completely taking it as a
deployment architecture that's why it's
mainly addressing those outer
architecture related principles here but
if you go and read the original spec
that you mention in the GitHub you will
find that it's addressing all these
three aspects that I explained
application deployment and the team
architecture so that reference you
referred is basically just focusing on
deployment architecture and in my view
that is not pure cellbase architecture
because it's more of a segmented
architecture
that is violating few primary Concepts
that we introduced in the cell
architecture that when we are getting
into the concepts I can explain detail
yeah maybe later when we get to a bit
more into details of the architecture
you can explain us this difference okay
now maybe we can just start to go into
more details now so I'd say starting to
ask you know what are the main parts of
a cell-based architecture yeah so
actually before answering that I would
like to add one more thing for the
previous question now in general when it
comes to a architecture style or a
pattern the patterns are more effective
if you apply the context to it so usage
of a pattern more effective pattern plus
context so in the previous example you
took that the definition of just
focusing on deployment it might be the
context it might be a infrastructure
team who took the architecture spec and
then mold it to the way that they want
it in the deployment architecture by
applying context so it became more
deployment oriented I just need to
address that because anybody who's
taking a pattern I think they need to
consider this by applying the context
before of course patterns always come
with a context of usage I ask a question
because if you look around Google
finding documentation about the dim
menion of the bulkhead pattern is
everywhere and so I wanted to check with
you what was the origin or if you had
anything to say about that because in
your documenting it I don't think there
is any mention of the bulkhead pattern
at all and by the way consider it yeah
all the links also are we'll provide all
the links in the page of the episode as
well so our audience can overl look
themselves yeah maybe we can actually go
into the details and starting with
talking about the main part of a
cell-based architecture and after we
Define them maybe also give an example
from real life yes so the uh even the
concept came with real life the analogy
of this started with Biology because in
real world everything created using
cells right like you get all the human
beings and then basically cells are
giving a structure to life so we thought
same thing in the software engineering
celles can give life to Modern Software
System so that's how the concept started
and we kind of cultivate the idea into a
architecture style so in the cell
architecture the foundation is a cell
Atomic unit is a component so I'll give
you examples what is a component and
since we spoke about microservices a
microservice can be a compon component
inside the cell and it can be a
integration it can be some kind of task
it can be something that generate events
all these type of workloads we treat it
as a component and then set of
components we call as a cell so cell has
a boundary and inside the boundary you
have the cell components so that
boundary that defines this grouping is
what we spoke about the bounded context
in the domain Riven design as well so
you have the components you have the
cell boundary now and there's a Gateway
at the top of the cell like in human
cells there's a membrane similar to that
you have this cell Gateway at the top
that controls the communication coming
to the cell so all the Ingress
communication to the components inside
the cell comes through the cell Gateway
so you can't directly communicate a
component without bypassing the cell
Gateway so that's a fundamental concept
that we have in the cell architecture
the igress calls that going out from the
cell basically the components inside the
cell it can go out it is not going
through the cell Gateway the ESS s are
going out and if you kind of imagine how
this works in a Enterprise architecture
that ESS call will go and hit another
cell Gateway because now you have these
cells operating inside the Enterprise so
any ESS call will go and hit another
cell Gateway and then do that particular
communication so the beauty of that this
provides a standardization of
communication within the Enterprise as
well as outside the Enterprise if I
getting into detail now all the
Northbound calls that's basically the
eess calls coming to the Enterprise come
and hit and go through the cell Gateway
and then the southbound calls that is
going outside the cell outside the
Enterprise that you can control by using
the egress policies that you put and
then the Westbound and eastbound that's
basically the internal communication
happening within the organization you
can control since all this communication
will hit a cell Gateway because of the
way that we are architecting and
controlling the communication within
that particular architecture can I ask
you a question so what is the main
reason for controlling V cell Gateway
what advantage do we get with this yes
so it's coming with another fundamental
principle that's a confusion in the
industry about API and the service in my
definition service is the implementation
API is the interface that you allow the
service to access or the execute so
there's a clear definition between an
API and a service so by applying that
principle you are exposing all the apis
from that cell Gateway and letting the
person who's invoking those services to
use the API instead of using the service
endpoint so that is the first reason
that why we are controlling the
communication from the Gateway second
thing now when you have a Gateway at the
top then you can apply the policies for
that particular domain by enforcing the
policies at the Gateway level so it's
really easy now you know exactly what
you have to do and you can define a set
of rules by telling who can access these
Services what type of security standard
that you should use and what type of
apis that you are exposing as example
you might decide okay for this
particular function I am having a rest
API for this particular function I am
having a grpc API and for this
particular function I'm having a graph
ql API all these things can be defined
at the cell Gateway level so that way
developers they have to fit into that
standard defined by the Enterprise
architecture and build these systems so
it's basically giving freedom for people
to do the development
with some guard rails that you put at
the Enterprise architecture level so
when microservices came into the picture
and these two Pizza teams introduced
into the
Enterprises it was great that you gave
lot of autonomy to these teams and how
you develop the stuff but it created a
issue by losing the control now if you
take it from the Enterprise architecture
level or from the business point of view
you didn't know what exactly the
developers were doing what language they
are using what third party libraries
they are using how they are securing
these stuff how this communication
happening and without calling a standard
endpoint with the contract or a
definition for that particular endpoint
it became Peter service or John service
that you have to go to Pete and John and
ask hey what's the definition of the
your microser
IA can access it so it became a problem
within the organization and the
Enterprise architecture lose the control
but you can't operate an Enterprise like
that you have to have set of Standards
you have to have set of best practices
and you have to standardize the
Enterprise architecture once you do that
then you can give lot of freedom for the
application development teams to operate
within those standards and develop these
system
without bringing uncertified or
unauthorized Technologies into the
Enterprise so those are the advantages
you are getting by putting that Gateway
at the top and have this seamless
integration at that level let me add one
more point before we jump into the next
topic so when you have the Gateway at
the top observability is really easy
because now the communication will
happen through a Gateway right because
because somehow it will hit one of the
cell gateways so you can easily capture
the observability data from that cell
Gateway and then have a full picture of
what is the round trip of a specific
transaction and then in addition to that
you can get the latency and then you can
get different type of communication
Styles happening because at the
architecture level you might assume this
is how the communication will happen
within the particular services but in
the runtime you might see different
styles or different patterns happening
right those things can be observed at
the run time as well as design time
because now you can capture that
communication data from the Gateway that
you put in top of each and every cell a
question about observability now to
mention that using a cell based
architecture say you access from the
Gateway you do the observability from
there but what about tracing you know
the calls where which service originates
the call and which service is going
because when you have to debug something
when there is a problem sometimes you
really need to go at the service level
understand what's going on yeah yeah so
that's two different levels right now
there's a inter cell communication and
there's the intell communication so
usually it's totally depending on how
the implementation works so I'll take
one example example one implementation
reference implementation that we have
done so in that particular uh
implementation between cells the
communication happens through apis and
you have the API gateways and within the
cell you have a service Mes in that
particular example we used ebpf and
celum to implement the service mesh and
the observability so you can capture all
these inter service communic ation
within that particular cell as well and
then you can get those tracing in
between the service calls happening
within the cell without any issue so
that's basically within the domain yeah
yeah my point was if you need to connect
several domains sometimes when servic is
interactive and Via Gateway you really
want to see the old path yeah of of the
C so is this still possible yes possible
it's possible so at the level one you
see the gateway to Gateway communication
and then when you drill down you can get
into that communication path and then
see what are the services got interacted
within that particular transaction and
then get all the details and then if
there are multiple interactions
happening in between the services you
can get that as well so all these things
are depending on how you implement the
cell architecture but from from the
architecture point of view yes it's
supported but you need to get it
implemented when it comes to the
implementation okay now a couple of more
things about the cell architecture then
I'd like to hear an example of a real
system in action if you like so we said
that is a cell of course is the main
part of a cell-based architecture then
components that are within a cell are
the things that make up a cell then the
gate with it is to communicate outside
the cell well at least to receive
Ingress Communications from other cells
but then also I found that there is also
a concept that is a control plane and
data plane as well so what are those
maybe just to Define them and what is
their purpose for our audience yeah so
the control plane basically now there
are two levels right one you have the
control plane at the top that you
provide the signals how the Enterprise
should operate so that's at the top
level and then you have the data plane
basically the sales are part of the data
plane and then within the cell you can
have a microcontrol plane basically the
Gateway act as a microcontrol plane to
have limited data and metadata to
operate the cell and provide the signals
to the services within the cell as an
example assume you have a public token
provider or STDs but if you implement
mtls within the cell or the services you
can have a private SDS to increase the
performance of that particular cell
within the cell so that SDS become part
of the local control plane of that
particular cell but if you look at it
from the high level sales are part of
the data plane and then you have the
control plane that controls how these
cells are orchestrating and then what
type of tokens that I should issue and
then the
observability then operational related
stuff all these things are coming at the
control plane that you implemented as a
platform service and managing all these
workloads running in the data plane okay
so as I understand it the control plane
defines if you like the way the cell
should well a few things I think there
are some looks like there Define some
policies but also some other things a
bit more on the technical level like the
API regist and all these things so in a
way since you are talking about
architecture that involves everything
involves not only the technical design
but involves deployment involves
operability the control plane defines
all the policies and some of the maybe
some of the system systems to enact some
of those policies so defining which cell
should communicate with which one some
aspects like this the data plane is a
more runtime kind of thing so exactly
the business logic and all the actual
workloads are running in the data plane
and the control plane is controlling how
this workload should run how they should
scale how they should communicate
basically that's where the control
center like if you imagine
the example analogy I took is airport
even you can take it as a train control
system all the trains are like the data
planes and the control center that sits
somewhere which managing the trains plus
the passengers is the control plane
basically okay and also a question about
also control plane because doing some
research around I was looking to this so
it seems that also parts of the control
plane are also the pipeline the
deployment pipeline as well is that
correct so because they basically that
is if you like is the architecture at
deployment time kind of architecture so
you define that in the control plane yes
so all the uh deployment related
decisions are taken by the control plane
as well and then we have to look at not
only the production system right before
you come into the production system you
have the dev environments you have the
test staging that's how the Enterprise
work right so we within an environment
how you deploy these things plus how you
promote these things from environment to
environment and then again if you are
going in detail about the deployments
how you can do blue green Canary type of
deployments all these things are
instructed by the control plane and then
running a data plane or number of data
planes why I use the term number of data
planes we are in an era of multicloud
and hybrid Cloud type of requirements
right multic Cloud comes with most of
the Enterprises are not stick into one
hyperscaler they like to use multiple
hyperscalers based on various reasons as
well as you can't ignore the data
centers right still Enterprises are
using these data centers and then having
a hybrid type of a setup so you can have
multiple data planes I think that that's
where things like kubernetes is helping
a lot in the current context because
kubernetes is helping you to have that
multicloud architecture in a proper way
because communties is like the Unix in
the infrastructure now so if you are
using kuties you can run it in any
hyperscaler Plus in your data center in
the same standards so with that I think
we need to think about a single control
plane with multiple data planes when it
comes to the Practical deployments okay
another question about boundaries of a
cell I was thinking so we talk about DDD
and so so far we said a cell is pretty
much a domain or maybe a bounded context
but are there any other criteria that
can be used to defend the boundaries
depending on some other things some
other constraints that are important to
particular company yeah I think how you
are organized basically so I think the I
would say 75 to 80% of the
implementations that I know use the
domain Ren design because it's a well
defined way of identifying these domains
but in some cases I have seen totally
depending on the teams like how you have
identified different teams and they are
responsible for set of things that they
do not coming from the domain Riven
design point of view rather the way that
they worked earlier and how they have
built their expertise so that team
definitions or team boundaries directly
mapped to cells that we have seen and
various other reasons like how they have
been operating at the moment and the way
they have have structured these Services
have been used as well but those are
like more organization specific I would
say there's no like a common way of
defining that the common way of defining
what we have identified is the domain R
design across organizations are there
any situations for example where maybe a
cell is pretty much an entire system and
there are some kind of replicas Maybe
data sharding or something used for say
reliability or availability purposes is
this a common case as well I have not
seen a single cell as a system but you
can
logically Define it at the architecture
level and then tell hey this is a system
I am treating it as a legacy cell or
something like that but it is at the
paper like or the architecture level but
implementation is just a system right
you have
to access it implementation level it
doesn't make sense to have something
like that implementation level it's
always like you have a set of workloads
that you group and then creating celles
I have not seen the scenario that you
explained okay you know I I was asking
because well doing some research around
so there was sell based architecture
apparently and slack and some other
companies and my understand
understanding from what I found on the
web about slack seems to be that this in
that case is pretty much about
availability zones and resilience so
it's kind of the cell seems to be slack
yeah the system and then it's kind of
replicating in different availability
zone so if something happens something
bad happens only a a small number of
customers are involved yeah I think the
way that I read that paper as well it's
completely looking at it from the
deployment architecture okay Point View
as we said before exactly it's perfectly
fine because they are addressing one
particular problem and then trying to
use cell architecture to address that
but the original idea and how we look at
it it's way more than that you can get a
lot of benefits more than the deployment
as you mentioned before because also
from your explanation basically now when
we were talking about the parts of a
cell the control plane is pretty much is
not simply the architecture of the
system per se but it's the architecture
of the context around it as well exactly
because we are talking about deployment
pipelines policies all sorts of things
basically everything around the system
that helps in building deploying and
operating the system exactly okay now
let's talk a bit about size so how many
cells should the system have it depends
on the complexity of the problem and
what size of an organization ation and
what portion of the system that you have
built with the cell architecture so the
number of cells it's really hard to give
a definite number because it totally
depending on the complexity but if you
ask the question how many components for
a cell then I have seen the best
practices so good designs it's around 10
components per cell and usually when I
am helping organizations designing
systems using cell architecture if it
goes beyond 10 components then we relook
at it and then divide it into subdomains
because if it is more than 10 it's
really hard to maintain as well as
there's a problem in that architecture
and the design that's kind of The Sweet
Spot that we have identified when it
comes to the number of components and
various implementation got various
number of cells like around 20 into 100s
because it's totally depending on the
design and the uh complexity of the
problem also from what you mentioned
before that ideally a team owns a cell I
would imagine that if you have more than
well you said 10 but let's say more than
a reasonable number of components yeah
it will be very difficult for single
team to keep track of what they are
doing exactly and then there's a
relation between the team and the cell
so a single cell cannot be owned by
multiple teams but a team can have
multiple celles okay now I can
understand that te can have multiple
celles now why a cell cannot be owned by
multiple teams because then the
fundamental things that we identified as
API is the way of commit communicating
and then the ownership and then the
domain knowledge you need to implement
that particular domain all these things
are breaking I'm not telling you cannot
do that you can do it but from the best
practices point of view if you start
letting different teams owning multiple
sales I mean single cell owned by
different teams then it will be really
hard to maintain it and then you will go
back to the same issues that we faced
without using cell architecture as well
so it's a best practice have you come
across companies that did that so with
several teams owning a single cell and
getting into problems with that then if
you got an example without mentioning
names yeah I think there are multiple
cases that we have seen like that then
there's a problem with ownership there's
a problem with release Cycles now you
have lot of dependencies within tee
boundaries so the way you can iterate
where you can frequently release will
get effected when you have this multiple
teams because this is not only about
technology right what is slow Downing in
most cases it's the people aspects and
the political aspect of organizations so
when you have this cross boundaries and
then multiple team invols then you have
to deal with this political aspects as
well that is slow Downing and then
having that particular team owning that
sell will have more impact then you can
do quick releases you can have proper
autonomy and be more Innovative in that
particular domain rather than you have
this cross boundaries and then there can
be situations as example now you have
Team a but you identified you might need
some expertise from Team B then
I think in proper agile terms then you
assign that person from Team B to team a
during that particular Sprint that's
perfectly fine but in that particular
development cycle that the person who
assign from Team B belongs to team a and
working with that particular team so
that way they can use that capabilities
but the ownership remain in that team a
not the team B okay and now another
question question about the cell so in
the reference architecture document in
GitHub yeah the one you created you
State this so I quote the number of
component component connections within a
cell should be higher than the number
that crosses the cell boundary hence one
approach would be to Cluster components
based on the connections now what do you
mean with that so basically if you look
at it now we have set of components
inside the cell right and there's
communication happening within those
components and then again there's
communication happening or coming to the
cell from different consumers who's
communicating with the API thatat you
Expos through the API Gateway so what we
have identified if there's no
significant communication happening in
between those services and if the number
of communication is limited you should
not divide the sell into multiple sales
because it's perfectly fine to remain
those services within that particular
cell boundary and if you see that
increase and you cannot manage that
that's where you need to consider hey
whether I should take some of these
Services out and then create a new cell
boundary so that's basically where we
are coming with the communication
the number of communications and number
of components and how you identify the
cell boundary that equation again it's a
best practice not a must to have thing
that when you are defining yeah I was
asking because I could imagine that if
you have a cell that implements a
central domain in a particular
Enterprise you may have lots of sales
using it and this Central domain might
have just a few Services inside in terms
of connections they might have a few
connections but they might be a lot of
connections to the cell itself yeah
which is against this particular
guideline it depends on the
functionality that you are providing
from that particular cell and the
communication Style again it can be uh
differ from the number of consumers
who's invoking the apis but I think when
it comes to the specification level what
we have identified those are the
guidelines as I said earlier even the
context might be different in some cases
so that's example that you took if that
is the case I think you have to apply
the context and then Define the cell
boundary okay what we have identify is
the common case in general what's
happening when you have the number of
domains and how you define the domains
and the communication okay and now I'd
like to talk a little bit about the
deployment of sales because it's like we
deploy sales but we deploy also services
within the sales yeah and we always talk
about basically cic CD for sales and
services now when we say with deploy
what do we do does it mean for example I
don't know if you are in the cloud a
particular I don't know AWS account we
declare it a cell and deploy services
for that cell there and create a Gateway
in that account for to communicate with
other celles this is just an example
popping from my head is trying to
understand what we mean with deploying a
cell yeah I think you can deploy and
Implement cell architecture in uh more
kind of a virtualized environment like
that it will work but it's more kind of
a static deployment in that case but
sell architecture is more effective when
it comes to a deployment like kues so I
will explain it from the kubernetes
point of view because an AWS a account
will be too large to treat it as a sell
but if you look at it from the kuber
point of view usually when it comes to
implementations people create crds to
define the cell boundaries but if you
are going for a basic deployment you can
treat a community's nam space as a cell
and a kuun is POD as a compon component
so you have the Pod that will scale the
component so set of PODS put it in the
name space can treat it as a cell for
somebody to get an idea of the
deployment mhm but okay if you deploy
this in a
nones environment then you need to have
Network level policies defined to
control the cell boundary and stop
community ation by putting a Gateway and
do some infrastructure level
configurations to create the cells and
we have not seen that many nones
deployments because most of the
deployments that we have seen is on top
of kuties and as I mentioned the common
way like pod and the Nam space but to
get it done properly you can write a
custom record definition or in
communities world we call it as a crd
and then Define how you are creating a
cell how you are deploying a cell and
then have those particular instructions
there and some of the implementations
they are using things like Helm charts
to Define this infrastructure basically
infrastructure as a code and then when
it comes to cicd and deployment level
you are using those scripts to create
sell as well as create components and
deploy it and in terms of deployment are
cell-based architecture more suitable
for cloud environments or they can work
just as well on on premises yeah so in
my view on premise means managed by the
organization and SAS means managed by a
provider okay Cloud means or in the
other way it can be
hyperscaler or it can be a private data
center because if you run a kubernetes
cluster in a private data center still
it's a cloud right managed by that
employment the particular organization
so if I reframe the question it will
work in both like in a hyperscaler
environment or in your data center but
having infrastructure orchestration
layer like kuties will help you to
implement it properly otherwise it will
become a static deployment that will
just separate the workloads but will not
bring the additional flexibility that
you can get that provide from cell
architecture so to answer your question
yes it can be a hyperscaler or it can be
a data center deployment but having
something like kubernetes will help you
to Great extent okay and now I'd like to
talk about implementing a cellbase
architecture so let's say an
organization that is considering to do
that now my first question for this is
for what kind of system would you
recommend the sale by sale based
architecture so I would say any like
there's no such system that you can pick
you can apply it to any kind of a system
but only thing if it is a distributed
system this is more applicable like if
you have like a more kind of Monolithic
systems then putting cell boundaries
will not change a lot it can change
little bit on encapsulating some of the
complexities and putting a API Gateway
on top of each and every system that's
perfectly fine but then again you will
not get the full benefit of cell
architecture by doing that so as long as
the system is distributed and you have
more decentralized architecture with
number of components you can apply the
cell architecture and there are two ways
of doing it you take the existing
distributed components and group them to
sales because you might have started
writing microservices you might have
writing these distributed workloads in
the system and you already have it right
you don't have to rewrite everything to
apply cell architecture in a situation
like that you can do an exercise by
listing all the components that you have
already and then group them by using
something like domain driven design or
any other mechanism and identify these
are the number of cells that I'm going
to have and for each and every cell I'm
going to distribute my existing services
so that is number one approach but if
you have a monolithical system and you
are planning to move into a distributed
architecture
then you can start from scratch and then
identify hey what are the microservices
that I'm going to write and then how I'm
going to organize these microservices
into sales and identify those sales and
identify those microservices or
components and start implementing the
new system by applying the cell
architecture Concepts and we have seen
both approaches especially like if you
take a larger Enterprise these things
are already existing right written bynet
or written by Spring boot or any other
technology so you kind of re architect
it by putting a modernization effort but
if it is a startup or an organization
going to do kind of a redesign they can
start with the second approach and do
the architecture and get into the
implementation if a company starting
from scratch a new system a green field
one they have this great idea for
assistant they don't have and say okay
we think we want to use a cell-based
architecture yeah how can they proceed
can they proceed incrementally for
example what is a typical way of
proceeding yeah I think iterative
approach and iterative architecture is
something I highly recommend because
people have a misunderstanding about the
architecture architecture is static it
is not architecture also iterative so
you can have a iterative approach but I
think you should have what's my end goal
or like what's my ideal architecture
identified then you can have a more pH
approach in phase one I'm just having
two cells and then putting everything
together and put two gateways and get it
done and in phase two phase three I'm
planning to divide these things into
number of cells and then distri
distribute
microservices and then have that end
State architecture or it can be I am
only building few microservices at this
point and I'm communicating with my
existing system for certain capabilities
so like that I think it's not only the
architecture and implementation right
you have to look at what business is
looking for what type of capabilities
that I have to provide first and then
again it can be a skill related thing as
well right you might not have the
required skill set within the existing
team to implement it so I think having
that analysis and then identify what is
the most feasible plan and then have
that pH approach will help again it's
depending on various factors I think
having a proper architecture exercise by
including the Architects and project
managers or the product managers will
help you to Define that face approach
and have it but I highly recommend to
have a more iterative approach than you
try to build these things because I'll
give you one example that one system
that we are being involved it was around
300 people and they had end State
architecture but it took around 3 years
to implement it but when you get into
three years most of the requirements you
identified in year one wasn't valid and
then business didn't see any advantage
of implementing a system like that so I
think maximum 3 to two weeks Sprints are
better that you should deliver quickly
experiment with that and then see
whether there's a value that you can
generate and get into the next phase is
the best because that's a problem that
we have seen that the technical
architecture and the technical
implementations are not aligned with
where the business is looking and what
type of capabilities that they are
looking at so I think having that
alignment and adjusting these type of
architecture approaches and
implementations will help the technical
teams to add more value to the
Enterprise okay so you just mentioned
skills so are there additional skills
that are required to implement a
cell-based architecture compared to the
ones required for a microservice one no
but I look at it from this angle because
you need to have a understanding about
application architecture you need to
have an understanding about the
deployment or the infrastructure
architecture as well as understanding
about how you divide and have a more
distributed system
okay and now I think I'll ask the final
question since we are getting to the
close costs what are the cost of a cell
based architecture compared to the cost
of microservice one let's take as a
reference a cloud yeah system so are
there differences in costs so I think if
you look at it from the infrastructure
cost there are few additional things
that you have to run right as a Gateway
for each cell those are little bit of of
additional things that you need to run
but then again if you look at it from
the overall gain that you are getting
from productivity stability of the
system and then flexibility that you
have as a overall system architecture
it's lot more so if you do like U
comparison between hard cost it can be
higher since you're adding things but if
if you look at it from the overall TCO I
think you will gain lot of benefit in
the longer run because of these
additional advantages that you are
getting so I think if you are doing a
proper cost estimation don't look at it
from the shortterm financial gains that
you are getting look at it from the
long-term as well as the soft gains that
you are getting as I mentioned about the
productivity and the flexibility because
the main issue that we have seen in the
Enterprise the business teams might have
great business ideas to implement or
provide new capabilities to your
customers or new business models that
you can implement but due to the
technical limitations you have you might
be not able to execute those things
right so having that flexibility in the
technical architecture and the
implementation you you can quickly
response to the business and then make
sure that you are implementing those
Concepts at the business level by
changing your architecture and then
doing new implementation in the
technical level so to get that
flexibility you can apply sell
architecture and get lot of benefits as
well as another thing that how disc
discoverable like how quickly you can
identify the things within the
Enterprise and how much you can reuse in
the Enterprise those are other things
that you need to consider so s
architecture is giving a great framework
for the organization to have that
Discovery flexibility ownership autonomy
all these advantages are getting so I
think there a huge cost benefit you are
getting in the longer run once you apply
this architecture style and Implement
your systems okay he thank you aanka I
think you've done quite a good job of
introducing this cell-based architecture
and is there anything we miss that you'd
like to mention I think we covered
almost everything but I would like to
recommend the uh listeners to read the
paper as well as there are a lot of
references that I have added as a
reference articles or additional
materials in the specification you can
read that and the specification released
under creative commment so if you think
you can contribute feel free to do that
send a full request I'm happy to review
it and include it and if you like to
contribute on articles or any other
details about the implementations that
you have done in cell architecture
please share it as well because then the
Architects and the developers who's
planning to use this architecture style
they can get a lot of benefit by reading
those implementation details so I would
like to add that as the last comment
okay thank you and the link to the
GitHub repository is in the references
we'll give for the show so the audience
will be able to access those easily and
so they will be able to contribute if
they wish to do so so thank you asanka
for coming to the show has been a real
pleasure and this is joavan aspon for
software engineering radio thank you for
listening like us thank you very much
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by it
e software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at
e-r. to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at Team
SE-R this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license
2.5 thanks for listening